Hello friends, my name is Anil Rajpurohit, I am the founder of M First Financial
Services, I have an MBA in Finance and have been working in the corporate sector for 15 years. Today
I am presenting to you
the comparison of benefits and features of term plans of top companies. Here you will see
the detailed comparison of the features of the top term plans of all the companies like Tata Birl Max Bajaj ICIC HDFC SBI LIC.
Generally, when a person purchases a term policy, he sees
how much premium he is getting. Premium is a key factor but
there are many such features which are very important along with the premium. For example,
when you are about to purchase a term policy or have already purchased it, do you know
that there is an option in your policy to increase the insurance cover with inflation? Can
your insurance increase by 5% or 10% every year? Is there such an option in your policy where
you feel that when you have turned 60 and your financial liability is complete, then
all the money paid will be returned? Is there such an option in your policy? Is
there such an option in your policy where if due to some reason you are unable to pay the full premium,
still your insurance cover continues for a certain period. For example, you
had to pay premium for 10 years and you paid premium for only four years, then would you
lapse completely if you have an insurance of Rs. 1 crore or if it increases by at least 40%, then
the insurance cover of Rs. 40 lakh will work or not? Have you
taken such a feature? Is there such a feature in your policy where let's say
unfortunately you become disabled in an accident, now in disability you
cannot earn, now you will need money for the house and how will you be able to pay the premium,
will the premiums be waived? Can you get money even if you are disabled?
Do you have such a feature in your term plan where you
can avail the benefit of critical illness up to Rs. 20 lakh, 50 lakh or even Rs. 1 crore and the premium does not increase for 20 years
because in health insurance the premiums increase
after every four years? There are many other benefits and features which
should be compared while purchasing the term policy and see whether this
benefit and feature is in my policy and the policy premium which has the most benefits
and features of this kind should also be checked once, you can purchase it along with that.
If you like my video, then
do subscribe to my YouTube channel Anil Raj Triple FS where you
will find 300 plus videos related to insurance which will help you in your financial planning.
So to understand the video or the plan in details, you
can visit my channel and to purchase the plan,
you can also purchase the plan from the link which I have given in the description
. So in this video, you will see the comparison of features, there
is eligibility criteria, option, there are many options within all these plans as well,
is there an option of return premium or not, is there an option of early ROP or not,
is there an option of joint life or not, will you get increasing insurance cover or not,
is there accidental cover or not Is there a rider for disabilities cover or not?
Is there a critical illness cover benefit or accelerated critical illness benefit?
How many critical illness benefits will you get as cover? If you want to take cancer cover separately,
then are any such riders available?
How much benefit can you get in terminal illness, can you get 50% or 100%?
In which plans is terminal illness benefit available? How much instant payment will you get as soon as you register the claim?
Which companies are offering special exit
features? You should compare them. Life Stage Benefit Cover Continuity Benefit
Premium Holiday in Income Production Cover Waiver of Premium
Parental Care Hospital Care Rider Maternity Cover Survival Benefit Maturity
Benefit Death Benefit Can you take the entire death benefit as a lump sum or
would you like to take the money as income? In which policies
is surrender benefit available? Reduce Paid Is there the benefit of discount or not? If I am a seller,
what discount will I get? What discount will I get if I buy the policy online?
If I am a female, what discount will I get? If I am purchasing insurance for the first time,
what discount will I get? If I am an employee of the same company, what
discount will I get? Are there any other term plans in that company or
are these the only term plans? What is their claim settlement ratio? Are loans etc. available under term policies?
Can I get a free look at this policy, can I cancel it,
can I get it revived? We will compare all these benefits and features in detail and
you can buy the policy which
you like the best according to the premium, features, claim settlement.
So, the companies that I have taken here include Tata AI, ICICI Pash, HDFC L, Axis Max Lef
Insurance, Bajaj Le Insurance, Birla Sun Life, Kotak Lef SBI Life and LIC's term
plan. Tata's Sampoorna Raksha Promise will be there, ICICI's I
Protect Plus will be there which was launched on 20 June 2025. HDFC L's Click to
Protect Super Term Plan is there, Axis Mah Le Insurance's Smart Term Plan Plus
is there. Bajaj's ETS to B, Birla's DG Shield, Kotak's Eterm, SBI's E Shield
Next and LIC's Yuva Term Plan. Here you
will see the comparison of benefits and features. If we talk about the minimum entry age, then the minimum entry age in all term plans
is 18 years. If we talk about the maximum entry age, then ICICI has it. A person up to 60 years
can purchase this policy. In LIC, a person up to 45 years
can buy Yuva Term Plan policy. In all other companies, a person up to 65 years can purchase a term plan.
Talking about the minimum sum assured, you
can purchase this policy with a minimum sum assured of 50 lakhs. The maximum sum assured in SBI is ₹75 lakh.
Talking about the maximum sum assured, there is no limit. You
can purchase any amount of insurance cover. In LIC, you can take a maximum of ₹5 crore. In SBI, if you
are a smoker, you will be able to take a maximum cover of ₹99 lakh only. There
is no such limit in other companies. Premium payment: Here, in most of the companies, you will get the option of regular pay, you
will get the option of limited pay, you will get the option of single premium.
In limited pay, you can
also select limited premium payments of 5, 7, 10, 12, etc.
But here, In Tata AI and HDFC L, you can
choose any premium payment term starting from 5 pay in limited pay to however long you want to pay, say 5
pay, 6 pay, 7 pay, 10 pay, 15 pay, 25 pay, 35 pay, 45 pay. In Tata and HDFC, it is written on the table here
that which premium payment terms you can select specifically. For example,
in LIC, you can take single pay, you can take the option of 10 years premium payment term, you
can take the option of 15 years premium payment term, you can take the regular one,
but if you want to keep the premium payment term for 20 years or 25 years or the policy
term for 45 years, then this kind of option is not available in them. Talking about the policy
term, in most of the companies, you can take the
policy term which is the maximum maturity age minus your entry age. The minimum policy term you
can take is 2 years as well as 5 years. You can also take 10 years. You
can see in the table that which minimum policy term is available in which plan.
Now let's talk about which options
are given to you in all these term policies. For example, in the Sampoorna Raksha Promise of Tata AI Life Insurance,
you are given two options - Life Promise and Life Promise Plus. Live Promise Plus
is the option of return of premium. Live Promise is the basic insurance
cover. The option of level insurance cover is ICICI Protect's
I Protect Smart Plus which has just been launched on 20 June 2025. Here you are
also given the option of Life Class Health. They have brought a rider of health
where you can take 20 to 60 critical illnesses and
the option of All in One is also given that in Life you can take the insurance cover of Level Cover.
In Life Plus you will get accidental cover. In Life and Health you
will get the benefits of critical illness. In All in One you will get Life Accidental Health and all You
will get benefits If we talk about options in HDFC Life Insurance, there is an option of Live and Live
Plus means that cover of accidental death benefit will be included here also.
In Axis Max Life Insurance, seven options are given in the policy. I
have explained all those seven options in detail. The video is already available on my YouTube channel.
If you want to watch separate videos of all the plans that I am explaining to you here, then it
is already available on my YouTube channel Anil Raj Triple FS. If you
want to see it in details also, you can watch it.
In Bajaj Reliance's E Touch Two, you are given three options, Life Child, Life Shield
Plus, Life Shield Plus means the one with accidental benefit and Life Shield.
ROP means the option of return of premium. In Birla, you are given 10 options.
In DG Shield plan, Kotak gives you three options. Life Live Plus means
accidental cover and life secure. Life secure means that there
will be life care cover benefits and the option of premium being waived off in case of total permanent disability in an accident
is available here. In SBI's EELS Next, you
will get the benefit of level cover and increasing insurance cover. The third
option they have given is Cover with Future Proofing Benefit, that is,
the option of life stage benefits is given. So if you want to add life stage benefits, that is, if you get married,
you can increase the insurance cover by 50%. If you
want to increase the insurance cover by 25% on the birth of a child, then this option is given here in option number three.
You can add it according to your need. LIC's Yuva
Term Plan also has level cover and the option of increasing sum assured is also given.
So these are different options. You can
choose which option you want to choose according to your needs.
Talking about the option of return of premium, you will get this option in Tata, HDFC, Axis Maxlife, Bajaj
and Birl's plan. ICICI Kotk SBI LIC
does not have the option of return and premium. ICICI has a separate plan called I Protect Smart Plus.
If you want to take a separate policy for return of premium, you
can do so. But under this plan, the option of ROP
is not available in ICIC. Talking about the option of early return and premium,
the option of early return and premium is available only
in Axis Max Life Insurance's Smart Term Plan Plus. That is, if you select an option there where you decide
that you should get half the premium paid at the age of 60 and the rest of
the money should be available after the policy term ends. But if you select this option,
then when you take 50% of the money at the age of 60, at that time your insurance
cover will also be reduced by 50%. If you had an insurance of 1 crore, then after that your
insurance cover will run from 50 lakhs for the rest of the policy term. Talking about
the joint life option, you will get the option of joint life in HDFC L, Birla
and in the term plan of SBI L, you will get the option of joint life. There is a mention of joint life in Tata
but it is not yet available for purchase, but you
can take it in HDFC L. For example, the husband purchased an insurance cover of 1 crore and the husband
died. You will have to select this option at the time of purchasing the policy at the time of inception.
Now suppose the husband dies, then the wife
will immediately get ₹1 crore and the wife's insurance cover will start from ₹50 lakh.
In future, if the wife dies, then the remaining ₹50 lakh will
be given to the nominees, who will be the children. You will see the same option in Birla as well.
In SBI Life, you can take a maximum cover of only up to 25 lakhs. This option is available there. Pay Better Hub
is known as If we talk about increasing insurance cover, then
you will get the benefit of increasing insurance cover in HDFC L, you will get it in Bla, you
will get it in SBI and you will get the option of increasing in LIC policy.
For example, if we talk about HDFC Life, here
your insurance cover will increase by 10% from the sixth year in every 5-year gap, that is,
the insurance cover will increase in the sixth year, then it will increase in the 10th year, then it will increase in the 15th year, so from the sixth to the 10th year,
suppose the insurance was of 1 crore, then it will increase to 1 crore 10 lakhs, then it
will become 1 crore 20 lakhs between the 11th and 15th year, in this way,
your insurance cover will increase by 10% in every 5-year gap. If we talk about Birla, there
is no need to wait for 5 years from inception, here you can select whether the insurance
cover should increase by 5% or 10%, according to that, your insurance cover
will be seen increasing from the first year itself. In SBI Life Insurance also, after the sixth year, your
insurance cover will increase in this manner in every 5 year gap, by 10% at a simple rate. In LIC
it will increase from the sixth year but then that gap of five years will not come. In the sixth year, it will be bigger, seventh year,
eighth, ninth, 10th. In this way, by the 15th year, your total sum assured, the base sum
assured, will double. There is a limit in all this that you
cannot go more than your base insurance cover, i.e., if it is 1 crore, it will increase only till 1 crore and then
your insurance cover will stop at 2 crore. Talking about the riders,
here on the screen you will see all the options or features other than the terminal engine.
These are all additional benefits which you
want to add in your policy by paying extra premium, you can do that. For example, first of all you take the option
of accidental cover, in case of death in an accident, then
along with the basic sum assured you will also get the sum assured of accidental cover rider, so here
in Tata AI Le insurance you can add a maximum rider of up to Rs 5 crore
for accidental cover, in ICICI you can add a rider benefit of up to Rs 3 crore,
in Kotk and Axis Max Lef you can add an accidental cover rider of up to Rs 1 crore,
in SBI also you can add an accidental rider of up to Rs 2 crore,
this rider is not available in LIC's Yuva Term Plan. As for disability rider,
you can take the additional benefit of disability cover in Tata Bla Axis and SBI, suppose your
base cover is of Rs 1 crore and you have also taken a disability rider of Rs 1 crore, then if there
is any total permanent disability If the death happens then you will get ₹1 crore, there is no need for death
but if we talk about Bajaj and Kotak then here you will not
get any separate amount, only the premium payment will be waived, that is, the base premium that you are paying, its
premium payment will be waived, you will not get any amount there. Talking about this rider in
HDFC Life Insurance, there you can take the amount option as well as
the income option, in the income option, for example, if you
took an accidental disability rider of 1 crore and there is a disability, then 1% of ₹1 crore i.e.
₹1 lakh will be given to you per month for the next 10 years. Let's talk about Critical Illness
Benefit Rider, if any serious disease occurs like cancer, heart attack,
kidney failure, this type of thing, then in addition to your base cover, you
have a big amount, whatever amount of rider you select, if any one of these
diseases is diagnosed, you get the entire money lump sum and the big thing is that
here you get it for a long time Your premium does not increase till then. Suppose,
if you have taken a health insurance policy, then after every four years
your premium increases according to your age, but if
you add critical illness in the term plan of life insurance, then it does not increase at every 5-year gap. Here in Tata, the
premium is reviewed after 5 years, but if I talk about ICICI, here
the premium will remain the same for 20 years, suppose you are taking the policy in 2025, then till 2045
your premium is going to remain the same and will not increase with age. Here
in Tata, you can avail the benefit of 40 critical illnesses. In HDFC, you
can get cover for 19 critical illnesses. In ICICI, you are given two options, you can also avail 20 critical illnesses.
You can also avail the option of 60. There are five options in Axis Max Lef, where if you
want to add 20 critical illnesses, 22 critical illnesses or 64 critical illnesses, you can do that.
In Bajaj, you have three options. 10, 25 and 60 critical illnesses In Birla, you
can get the benefit of 40 critical illness cover. In Kotak, you
will get the benefit of 37 critical illnesses. Critical illness rider is not available in SBI and LIC. Accelerated
critical illness means that where you will not get any additional add. Suppose
you have taken a policy of 1 crore and you have added critical illness of 20 lakhs there, then in
the earlier critical illness benefit rider that I mentioned, you get 20 lakhs separately
and 1 crore is given separately on death. Accelerated critical illness
means that suppose you have taken a basic cover of ₹1 crore and suppose you
have taken critical illness of 20 lakhs, then if a critical illness occurs there, you
will get ₹20 lakh. Then if death occurs in future, you get ₹1 crore - 20 lakhs 80 lakhs for
accelerated critical illness. The premium is comparatively less than the advanced
critical illness. So, these riders are available only
in Birla right now. Earlier, it was available in ICICI also but recently,
in the new product that they launched, they have removed accelerated and
have started giving you additional cover benefit as an add-on. Here, let us talk about cancer cover
separately. If you want to add a rider only for cancer, then this option is available only
in HDFC's Click to Product Super. Talking about terminal illness benefit,
this terminal illness benefit is available; you do not have to pay a separate premium for it.
In Tata, 50% of the sum assured is available. Suppose you had an insurance cover of Rs. 1 crore and
some such illness occurs where cure is difficult and the doctor gives in writing
that this patient may die within six months, then 50% of Rs. 1 crore
You will get it while you are alive, the rest will be given on death. In HDFC and Bajaj you
have a limit of up to 2 crores, there if you have taken a cover of up to 2 crores, then
you will get the entire 2 crores on terminal illness, you will not get anything on death, but suppose
you have taken a cover of 5 crores there and you have a terminal illness, then you
will get 2 crores on terminal illness and the remaining 3 crores will be given on death, so in this way
Birla, SBI has a limit that brother you can take up to 50%, in SBI also you
can take terminal illness up to 2 crores, terminal illness is not available in Kotak,
in Birla you can take up to 50% and the maximum is 2 crores, but
there is no such limit in ICICI's I Protect Plus plan, there is no such limit, there if you
have taken an insurance cover of 5 crores, if there is a terminal illness, then you
will get the entire 5 crores on terminal illness, there is no such limit that you will get only 1 crore maximum, there
is nothing like this on death, you will get the entire money together because
Insta Payment on Claim Intimation Suppose there is a death and the family members
have just registered the claim within one working day, Tata ICICI Pidencal and Axis Max Lef
Insurance will give you a certain amount like Tata and ICICI
will give ₹3 lakh and Axis Max Lef will give you instant money up to ₹2 lakh, the rest of
the claim amount will be settled and you will get the rest of the money. Let's talk about
special exit benefit, technically you call it zero cost term plan, many
people can also call it surrender benefit in a way, let's say
your age is 35 years and you took insurance cover till the age of 80, at the age of 60 you feel
that my financial liabilities are over now, the children have grown up,
they have started earning on their own, now if I close the policy and I want to withdraw the money,
then I can take it, this is called special exit benefit, you
do not have to pay any additional premium for this, it is an inbuilt feature Surprisingly this option is not available in Tata
, nor in Birla, nor in SBI, nor in LIC,
but this option is available in ICICI HDFC Axis Max, Bajaj and Kotak. Let us assume that
you took a policy of ICICI Plan at the age of 35 or 30 years, then at the age of 55,
that means the policy term is of 25 years or
at the age of 60, whichever is early, at that time you can exercise this option.
Let us talk about the life stage benefit. Life stage benefit increases with time as more
example, when you are purchasing a term plan policy, at that time you are unmarried but when
you get married, when your financial liabilities increase, and you want
your insurance cover to increase, then on marriage you can increase the insurance cover by up to 50%.
In some companies there is a limit that you
will get a maximum benefit of only Rs. 50 lakh, but in ICICI, suppose you have taken an insurance cover of Rs. 3 crore and you have to add Rs. 3
crore when your Even if you are married, you can add it. Suppose if the first
child is born or the second child is born, even at that time, if you
want to increase the insurance cover, you can do so. If you take a home loan,
even while taking a home loan, if you want to increase the insurance cover, you can do
so. You can see in the table how much percentage can be increased in which company. Let's talk about cover
continuation benefit. Cover continuation benefit is such a unique feature that it
is inbuilt. There is no need to pay any separate premium. If at any time
you feel that in this financial year, I am facing some financial problems, I
will not be able to pay the premium this year, but you do not want your policy to lapse, then
you intimate the company 30 days in advance that Bhaiya, this year I will not
be able to pay the premium, then your insurance cover will continue. Suppose,
even if there is a death in the year in which you did not pay the premium, the family members will get the full death benefit. This is an excellent
unique feature launched by the companies. Like, during the time of Covid, many people
had financial problems, that insurance If the premium is not paid in the policy, the policy
gets lapsed, but on exercising this option the policy will not lapse,
but next year when you go to pay the premium then you will have to pay the premium not paid this year and
the premium of next year together, so
you will get this option in Tata, ICICI, Axis, Bajaj,
this option is available in these four companies. There is also an option of premium holiday
which is available in Bajaj's E-Touch. Bajaj's E-Touch also has cover continuation benefit and
premium holiday benefit as well. Premium holiday means that here you
You decide that as I told you, in policy continuation,
you have to pay the premium for both the years together next year, but in premium holiday,
you do not have to pay the premium together, you do not pay it for one year next year,
you have to pay the premium for the same year next year, but then for example, if you
had selected premium payment for 10 years, then in policy cover continuation benefit, you
have to complete the premium within 10 years only, suppose you did not pay for the eighth and fifth years, then
in the sixth year you have to pay for both the fifth and sixth years, but in premium holiday, if you
did not pay for the fifth year, then you have to pay the premium for the sixth year, seventh year, eighth, ninth, 10th
and 11th year also because you did not pay for the fifth year, in this way,
you can exercise this premium holiday also thrice, so there should be a gap of 5 years in it.
Income protection cover is available only in option number seven of Axis Max Life Insurance.
What do most of the customers do now, when they purchase a term policy, they
decide that how much sum assured do I want, whether I want 1 crore or 2 crores. This is
the way they purchase the policy but in this option the customer decides
that suppose when I die, how much money should come per month for my household expenses,
should I get ₹1 lakh, ₹50,000 or ₹2 lakh, so you decide the amount
that I should get ₹1 lakh every month in case of my death, then my nominee or my wife
should get it every month, so you can select this option. Let's talk about waiver of
premium. Waiver of premium means under which
conditions the premium increases are waived, for example now if we talk about HDFC L, Axis Max Le
and Bla, then here if there is a critical illness or total permanent disability,
in both these cases the premium increases are waived. In Tata AI, the premium increases will be waived in case of terminal illness,
in Bajaj , the premium increases will be waived in case of terminal illness and total and
permanent disabilities. In K Coke you have option
number three Where the premium
increase is waived only on permanent total and permanent disabilities. Let's talk about parental care rider or parental care
benefit. These are unique benefits and features. I will try to explain them to you here.
First of all, let's understand the HDFC parent secure
option. Let's assume that there is a 35-year-old person named Ajay and his parents
are 65 and 70 years old and they purchase a term policy of ₹1 crore from HDFC
in which they select the parent secure option. One of their parents is diabetic
and if they think that if they die,
how will they manage the expenses for their life time, then they select this option in this policy. Now, let's assume
that Ajay dies after 10-12 years, then 7% of ₹1 crore i.e. ₹1 lakh every year
will keep coming to the parent nominee for life. Now, from both the parents Suppose
the husband dies first, then as long as the other parent is alive, the ₹7 lakh
will continue to come to them. Now let's take another example, let's assume that first the parents
die, then the husband dies, then the entire ₹1 crore is a lump sum which
will be given to their nominee, be it wife or children. Talking
about Bajaj Life Insurance's Parental Care, this is a rider. Here,
along with the base cover, you can take a separate benefit of the rider, whose benefits
will be separate. Here, if death occurs, then
105% of the total premium paid for the rider will be received and an income will be generated which will be from 0.1% to 0.5% of your sum assured, which you
will get per month for lifetime, the parents will be the nominee. For example, a
40-year-old man takes a term policy of ₹1 crore and along with that he takes a policy
of ₹50 lakh. Parental care rider is also added, where the premium
will be only around ₹8,000 and they are taking a rider of ₹50 lakh for 35 years. Now suppose
they die after a few years, then the total
105% of the premiums paid by them will be received immediately and the insurance cover of 1 crore will be received separately,
but the benefit of the rider is, here in the example, I have taken 0.2% of the income, so
0.2% of ₹1 lakh comes to ₹10,000 every month, which will keep coming to the nominee, who is the parents,
for life time and if you had kept 0.5, it would have come to ₹25,000 per month. So in this
way, you can also get this rider added according to your need, if your
parents are old and they have some health issues or there
are a lot of medical expenses and you feel that after your death, they will not be able to take care of them. a lot of money will be needed
If unfortunately something happens to you, then how will your family manage their money?
For this, you can add a separate rider which will
give them a big amount every month. Hospital rider is available only in Tata AI policy. Hospital
care means that let's assume that you do a job and your family
gets an income because of you, but unfortunately you get sick due to some reason and
get admitted in the hospital, then now you will stop getting income, that is, your salary. Or if you
are starting a shop or office, then the income will stop there. Suppose you
are getting treatment in the hospital for some time, then here you can get
up to 5% benefit of a rider. Suppose you have added this rider of ₹1 lakh, then
you will get benefit of ₹5,000 per day for the number of days you stay in the hospital. If you get admitted in the ICU,
then plus ₹5,000 more, that is, ₹10,000 will be given to you every day. You will get its benefit every day.
So if you want to add this kind of rider also, where there is a loss of income
on a daily basis, then it can cover it. Let's talk about maternity benefit,
it is available only in Axis Max Life Insurance, in no other company because this
is a term policy, not health insurance. Maternity cover
is available in health insurance policy. There are very few such options in life insurance cover. So
this is an option in Max Life Insurance, where if there
are complications related to maternity, then you
will get up to 50% benefit of the rider and 50% if the new born baby has any health issue, which is
called congenital disorder in pure Hindi, if there is any such problem, then 50% of the sum assured
will also be available at that time as a maternity benefit. I mean survival benefit, that is,
as long as the policy is running and you are surviving, during that time, whether you
can get income or not. This option is given only in option number nine of Birla.
Where you get an income of 0.12% of the sum assured every month. Suppose you
have taken a policy of ₹1 crore, you will get ₹12,000 per month, you will get ₹144000 as annual income, but as soon as the income
starts coming, your sum assured will keep reducing by that amount. Talking about
maturity benefit, here in any of the policies that I
have mentioned, there is no maturity benefit in the product. Unless you
have taken the option of return and premium, you get back the money paid there.
Talking about death benefit, here in death benefit, you
will get the total sum assured minus if you have taken any benefit of terminal illness
or accelerated critical illness, then that will be minus, otherwise
you get the entire 100% money on death. Talking about the option to take death
benefit in installment, if you want to take money in installment, suppose
your 1 crore There was a cover of Rs. 1 crore if the death happened, do you want to take lump sum or do you
want to take it as income or you have taken a little money lump sum, suppose
you have taken 50 lakh lump sum, if you want to get an income of 50 lakh then you can
take this income for 5 years, 10 years or 15 years, you can take it, different
companies have different options, you can see in the table here for how many years you
can take the income, if we talk about surrender benefit, then in regular pay there
is no surrender benefit in term plan, but if you have taken limited pay policy then you
get surrender benefit, let's talk about reduce paid up benefit, this
is a very good feature of RP benefit, which was available in limited pay of almost all the companies till before Covid,
nowadays many companies have stopped it, now it
is available only in the policies with retention and premium, that too it is available only in the companies mentioned here,
but even here There are two unique ones, SBI and Kotak. Here
also there are plans without return of premium. They also have this feature of RPU.
RPU means reduce paid, reduce paid. It means that suppose there
is a 35 year old person who wants to pay premium for 10 years. He
takes an insurance cover of Rs 1 crore for 40 years. Let us assume that after 4 years,
for example, due to some reason he does not want to pay the premium
and is not able to pay it in future. So he had to pay for 4 years and 10 years, that means he
has paid 40% premium. So 40% of Rs 1 crore i.e. 40 lakh insurance cover will still continue.
When there is death in future, the family will get Rs 40 lakh. But the company
has an option for the rest of the things. Suppose if the premium is not paid, the policy will be left after that.
In case of death, the family members will not get even Rs.1. All the companies give you discounts in different ways
in term policies, which can be different.
You will get salary discount separately. If you purchase the policy online, there is a separate discount. If you
are a female, you get a separate discount. If you are an employee of that company, you get a separate
discount. There can be different types of discounts as well. For example, if we
talk about Tata AI's Sampoorna Raksha Promise, here if you are a salaried person, you
will get 5% discount. If you purchase online only for the first year,
you will get 10% discount for the first year only and if you are a female, you will
get an additional 15% discount. Talking about ICICI PDL, here if you are a regular salaried person and
paying regular premium, you get a discount of 12.5%. If you are paying limited pay, you
will get a discount of 15%. If you purchase online for salaried people, there
is an additional discount of 5% and if you are a female, you will get an additional 15% discount. HDFC
Life Insurance There is a discount of 5% only on online payment. Apart from this, if you
are an already existing customer of HDFC L Insurance, you will get a discount of 2%. Axis Max Le
Insurance has a discount of 15% for cell-riders. For the first year,
you will get only 2% discount in single pay. No discount is available online.
But if you are a female, you will get a 15% discount. The 15% discount for females
is not for the first year but for every year. And
if you are an existing customer, you will get an additional 15% discount.
And if you are an employee of Max Life Insurance, you
will get a discount of 5%. So let's assume that you already have a
policy of Axis Max Life Insurance, suppose you have a policy of Rs 10,000 and you are going to take a term policy and
you are a female, then you got 15% discount for existing customers, 15% discount for females,
if you are a cell-rider, you get an additional 15% discount. So, the discount is up to 45%.
If we talk about Birla Sun Life Insurance, here 4% discount is being given only
on online purchases. All the discounts that I
am telling you, I have taken from the brushes that they have mentioned. These discounts
may increase or decrease in the future, may also be discontinued, and more may come. The company
keeps updating them from time to time, but once you have taken the policy, it does not change.
In Kotak Life Insurance's e-term, if you are a salaried person, you get a 5% discount for the first year
and if you are an existing customer, there is a discount of 5%.
In SBI Life Insurance, if you purchase from SBI's website itself, you
will get a discount of up to 4%. No such discount is available in LIC, but
they give the policy to females at a slightly cheaper rate. Let's assume that the age of a male is 35 years and
the age of a female is 38 years, then the premium of both will be the same.
Now as you have seen that every company has a term plan, but all these companies
have other, third and other term plans as well which they have launched
according to different needs. So for example Tata has the Sampoorna Raksha Promise
along with Maharsha Supreme Select which is a pure term plan which
is available only to a person earning a minimum of Rs. 15 lakhs. Plus they have Param Raksha Plan
which is a term plus ULIP plan. Here you get natural cover, accidental cover,
disability cover and if you survive, you
also get returns according to the share market. So whenever I talk about term plus ULIP, I
will use the word Tulip. So you can understand that we are talking about term plus ULIP.
Here, ICICI Pashchi also has other plans in which I Protect
Smart Plus has the option of return premium. There is also the option of Protect and Gain.
Protect and Gain is their Tulip policy. Axis Maha Insurance has Star
Tulip policy and they also have Smart Secure Plus plan. Plus
they also have an Elite plan. Bajaj L has I Secure to Normal plan which
is available for people with low income and education. Invest Protect Goal
is their Tulip policy. In Kotak L, the name of the Tulip policy is Tulip. SBI Life Insurance
has two separate term plans by Smart Childs Smart Shield Premier.
LIC has a term plan by Jeevan Amar. So if your need is different, then
you can also look at these term plans. Talking about the claim settlement ratio,
as per the updates on their website till June 20, 2025,
Tata AI has 99.41%, ICICI PSL has 99.30% and HDFC L Insurance has 99.3%.
of 99.50 Axis Max Le Insurance has been number one
for the last 3-4 years, 99.70 this year Bajaj Reliance Le Insurance
has 99.25 Bla's latest update is not out yet, but last year it was 98.40 Kotak's
last year was 98.25 SBI's is 98.39 LIC is also 98.15
Almost all companies have a claim settlement ratio of above 98,99,999 So you can
purchase the term plan of any company according to your needs,
according to your premium affordability, according to the features that seem right to you and if you are
getting different types of discounts, female etc., you
can decide accordingly and purchase it So if you want to understand the term plan, if you want to
understand the product of the term plan, then
you can go to Anil Rajput Triple FS's YouTube channel and understand by watching the video And if you want to purchase a term policy, let's assume
that you like any of these term plans, you can purchase it You know
that term plan is very important, you want to purchase it, but in the village,
city or town where you live, the company whose
plan you liked is not there, the branch is not available or
in the city where you live, you are not getting any agent or any advisor
who can help you in purchasing the policy, so I have given the link in the description below,
you do not need to go anywhere, whether you are in a village or a small town, you
can purchase this term policy sitting at home and that too with a discount because if you
purchase online, you will also get additional discount, so if you
liked this video, then before leaving,
definitely subscribe to my YouTube channel Anil Raj Triple FS, if you want
a video on a particular topic or on a particular product, then you must write about it in the comment box,
I will try to make a video on it and in future, till now you have seen that I have
made a video for pure term plan which is for high income and higher education people,
where they should take term policy For those with low income or less education, I
will launch another comparison video in some time and if you
want to purchase the policy by comparing term plus unilip, then that video
is already available on my channel, you can watch it. Thank you so much, Jai Hind.